so we're talking the other day about
diligence and how that is
and how that is
practice really how one invokes
diligence in general hmm
in general hmm
you know when you
by mindfulness danger accomplishment of
danger burial not being complacent
basically yeah
and something about how if there you
were sitting around
relaxing and some a task came up
I mean that conversation right right
yeah get up and do it get up and do it
yeah even though that you
even though that you
you kind of wanted to lay down and rest
yeah yeah like even though I felt like I
don't have to do it at a time I earned
this rest
I would still do it just so the Mind
does not take it that laziness and it
doesn't become hindrance because he can
that's why people often feel even if
they say heaven felt justified in
centrality before
when they start working or getting sort
of engaged and completing tasks and
stress enduring stress and during that that
enduring stress and during that that
hardship of any kind
in the world or as much then centrality
becomes kind of justifiable like I
deserve this I need to rest and since
you see no other basis of rest
sensuality becomes your rest
so until you can see any different bases
than resting on sensuality you can't
take rest for granted
so does that mean you should never rest
well from one point of view yeah you should
from one point of view yeah you should
never let your guard down
from another point of view yeah well no
do go and sleep that's a form of rest to
I don't know go for a walk sit quietly
because seclusion that's a form of rest
but you got to start Discerning it and
even then don't take it for granted
don't feel justified in doing it because
again the disturbances of the world the stress
the disturbances of the world the stress
does not come on a kind of side Town
smells this touches comes on a kind of
undeveloped mind it's still not people
craving so if you need to rest from your stress
so if you need to rest from your stress
that you still assume to be coming from
the world and sense objects means you're
still carrying problem with you even
when you're resting
because you're resting from a wrong
thing
but then if you uproot the possibility
of craving resistance towards whatever's
felt then you're always addressed
then you're always addressed
even when you're working or having your
limbs chopped off by Highway robbers as
I should say
you won't have a need to rest because
you're not Disturbed to begin with
you're not stressed
so that's just to show that you gotta
know you must not forget
where the problem and the solution is
and stop equating justification for rest
with kind of implication that the
problem came from the distress came from
these things in the world
disturbance doesn't come from things
it comes from a
undeveloped mind
from greed a virgin delusion that's it
those are the three root causes of any
formal disturbance
so yes initially until you can see
through that take a break from seemingly
disturbing things we draw keep keep the
presets develop virtue step away
just so that you can see the truly
disturbance comes from your mind
but if you never relinquish the view the
disturbance comes from these things and
concentration helps me not see these
things you're never gonna stop being disturbed
you're never gonna stop being disturbed
how much you rest no matter how much you
rest no matter how protected your
environment becomes no matter how strong
your concentration is
it will have to run out and you're back
onto being disturbed because you're
carry the root of disturbances with you
because greed diversion delusion are not
uprooted by focusing hard away from them
moment to moment moment to moment
they're reported by full understanding
of the danger of parallel gratification
Escape in regard to them
so Taming of the mind to attempt through
guarding of the sensors through Taming
of this uh the the behavior through
keeping the presets that is the
development and there is never a justifiable break
and there is never a justifiable break
from keeping the precepts or being
watchful of your intentions
there is a justifiable break from being
engaging with the centers or from
concentrating away from the senses you
need a break from both
but you never need a break from
mindfulness from recollectedness from
from right memory as the Buddha said you
can't have too much of mindfulness it's
impossible if you are that's not what mindfulness
if you are that's not what mindfulness
is [Music]
[Music]
having done rightly an arahanto it's a
he doesn't need a holiday
he doesn't need a holiday because he is
not Disturbed to begin with
Disturbed to begin with
even with things that people usually
ascribe the disturbances too oh it comes
from side sounds melt this touches from
having to listen to this having to look
at this having to do this that's why my
mind is disturbed because he said
something upsetting because she didn't
do something I require her that's why my
mind is Disturbed and what about
essentiality it's not the issue it's
just that I get disturbed by it so if I
just make my mind strong enough to be
able to be sensual and not get suffering
well that's that's contradiction terms
then because sensuality
if you were to engage with it to any
extent to that extent you would be
disturbed because otherwise why would
you engage with it if there is no
Central pressure of central desire even
some like slight aspects of it
why would you be engaged why would you
be scratching if there is not a
slightest Stitch yet slightest Stitch
means there is a degree of disturbance
so you saying it's not disturbing yet
I'm engaging with it it's a
contradiction in terms oh it doesn't
scratch it doesn't itch but I'm
scratching it
why would you do such a thing
so the disturbance comes from greed mine
not free from greed aversion delusion
that need to be understood
through contemplating as you said many
times Well through sensory string
guiding in the sense those watchfulness
of your intentions Discerning of your
intentions and then contemplating
dangers of engaging with things with
desires and intentions rooted in greed
aversion distraction
and that's just it's basically reflexive
pondering of the right kind sustaining
that context throughout the day memory
recollecting the right things the right
dangers they will then keep your mind
composed from slipping away and doing
and committing back to those actions
that perpetuate the problem of
undeveloped mind
so that's what the practice is that's
where the true non-disturbance comes
from if in the meantime you need to rest well
if in the meantime you need to rest well
ask yourself why do you need to rest if
I need to calm down through
concentration why am I Disturbed in the
first place
is it because I wasn't concentrated
enough or is it because I didn't even see where
or is it because I didn't even see where
the problem came from all I know is I'm
in suffering now
so understanding is the only only way
out